A Guide to the Papers of Richard Cutts, 1753-1886
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of Richard Cutts, 1753-1886
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
10029-e
There are ca. 185 items (1 Hollinger box) in this collection.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This collection was given to the University of Virginia Library by Susan Lyman, Charleston, South Carolina, on 28 April 2001.
Biographical/Historical Information
Richard Cutts (1771-1845) was a U.S. Representative from Massachusetts, born on Cutts Island, Saco, Maine. He graduated from Harvard in 1790, beame a member of the State house of representatives, 1799 and 1800. Cutts was then elected as a Democrat to Congress, 1810-1813. Later he was appointed as superintendent general of military supplies, 1813-1817, and as Second Comptroller of the U.S. Treasury, 1817-1829.
Scope and Content Information
This autograph collection consists chiefly of letters to Richard Cutts. The letters are from prominent individuals, primarily of Maine and Massachusetts and other areas of New England.
Also present are invitations from Dolley Madison and [Lydia Howard] Sigourney; a commission for Walter Coles Cutts as midshipman, signed by John Quincy Adams; a commission for Richard Cutts as a Massachusetts Justice of the Peace, signed by Governor Joshua Strong; envelopes franked by Dolley Madison (no content) and one envelope franked by President James Madison; brief genealogical materials on the Cutts family; two letters to Lucia Beverly Cutts (1851-?), grand-niece of Dolley Madison, concerning Memoirs and Letters of Dolly Madison: wife of James Madison, President of the U.S.; news clippings; an oath of Richard Cutts to perform the duties of Superintendent General of Military Supplies of the United States sworn before Joseph Forrest; obituaries for Colonel Richard D. Cutts, Dr. Harry M. Cutts; and General Richard D. Cutts (1817-1883); recepits for pew rent and a minister's salary; a poem addressed to the Honorable John Quincy Adams; a printed appeal for biographical information from Harvard graduates from John Langdon Sibley; promissory note signed by James Madison; and a silhouette fo Martha Jefferson Hackley Cutts.
Contents List
- CORRESPONDENCE
  - [James Anderson (1793-1808)?] "Mercator," to unknown 1811 April 19
    Warns recipient that he will be removed from office and replaced by Richard Cutts for political reasons
  - John Jacob Astor (1763-1848) to Richard Cutts 1817 March 10 and April 17
    Congratulates Cutts on his new position and discusses the purchase of a new set of china for Mrs. Cutts
  - John Martin Baker to Richard Cutts 1811 July 8
    Ships the red wine ordered by Cutts
  - George G. Barrell to Richard Cutts 1922 March 24
    Introduces his partner to [James?] Monroe
  - Nicholas Biddle (1786-1844) to Richard Cutts 1828 July 23
    Notifies Cutts of an unfavorable decision by a committee of the Bank of the United States concerning a debt
  - Barnabas Bidwell (1763-1833) to Richard Cutts 1808 Dec 19
    Comments on the recent election of Madison as raising the spirit of the Republicans in his area and the death of Governor Sullivan as not harming their chances in next year's gubernatorial election
  - William Blunt to Richard Cutts 1815 February 22
    Requests his help in securing command of a revenue cutter from the district of Frenchman's Bay west to the Penobscot River in Maine
  - John Parker Boyd (1764-1830) to Richard Cutts 1813-1814, 5 ALS
    Discusses the participation of himself and his men int eh Battle of Chrystler's Farm on November 11th and requests his aid in avoiding duty at New Orleans
  - Joseph C. Boyd to Richard Cutts 1813, 3 ALS
    Thanks him for his assistance in securing army and other appointments for himself and his friends, mentions conflict between local Federalists and Republicans, especially concerning Colonel Learned
  - John Chandler (1762-1841) to Richard Cutts 1809 February 4, ALS
    Warns that the British influence in New England might pave the way for a separation of the states due to the reaction to the Embargo, referring particularly to the influence of the letter rom Rimothy Pickering to the Governor
  - John Chandler to Richard Cutts 1812 December 5, ALS
    Makes disparaging remarks about the New York militia refusing to cross the lines at Lake Champlain and to fight their way to the Saint Lawrence River, partly from the political motive of outsting Madison from the presidency by military disasters
  - Langdon Cheves (1776-1857) to Richard Cutts 1820 January 15
    Acknowledges the receipt of a proxy from Cutts to him while president of the Bank of the United States
  - Edward Coles (1786-1868) to Richard Cutts 1822 April 12, ALS
    Coles, cousin of Anna Cutts, asks Richard Cutts to pay the taxes on his lots in the City of Washington to prevent their being sold for taxes, and to find out if Mr. Crawford intends to have a public sale of lands at the Illinois land office
  - Edward Coles to Richard Cutts 1828 October 18, ALS
    Conveys his consternation at being appointed by Mr. Rish to examine the land offices of India when he had requested an appointment in Illinois
  - Isaac A. Coles (1780-1819) to Richard Cutts n.d.
    Has received the forms for making his quarterly returns, and teasingly asks Mrs. Cutts to search for him a wife
  - Orchard Cook (1763-1819) to Richard Cutts 1809, 1814, 3 ALS
    Recommends several people for office and defends his service in office, protesting that he was not reappointed
  - Ellen Wayles Randolph Coolidge (1796-1876) to Anna Cutts 1824 Feb 1
    Writing from Monticello she regrets being unable to accept her invitation to visit; expects Mrs. Madison to make her usual visit to Monticello in April, and comments on the extreme cold
  - William H. Crawford (1772-1834) to Richard Cutts 1829 May 5
    Discusses Cutts' removal from office
  - Anna Cutts to Dolley Madison [1814 Aug?]
    Writes a moving note during the British attack on Washington, "My Sister Tell me for gods sake where you are and what going to do -- I have only time to ask Mr. C- to take out he fore part of the carriage -- put in the piano -- and anything he can get in there or in a wagon if the British are coming -- we can hear nothing but what is horrible here -- I know not who to send this to -- and will say but little"
  - [Anna Cutts] to [Richard Cutts] n.y. September 17
    Plans to leave Montpelier for Washington with her brother James and informs her husband that Mr. Madison has had two letters from R. Smith, who says [Andrew?] Jackson refuses to make communication until the arrival of the President
  - Charles Cutts (1769-1846) to Richard Cutts 1814 June 23
    Asks for the help of his cousin in securing the post of Secretary of State
  - Dominicus Cutts to Richard Cutts 1812 March 6
    His brother writes concerning financial matters
  - Foxwell Cutts to Richard Cutts 1809 October 23 and November 13, 2 ALS
    His brother forwards his mail and mentions the launching of the ship [ Castor?] and other related business matters
  - Richard Cutts to Thomas Cutts 1807 February 19
    Refers tonews of a treaty in London, probably the Monroe-Pickney Treaty and the surrender of Aaron Burr and his forces to the militia of the Mississippi Territory
  - Richard Cutts to Thomas Todd 1817 May 16
    Refers to his recent appointment and the fears of the friends of James Monroe upon his appointment of John Quincy Adams as Secretary of State
  - Thomas Cutts to Richard Cutts 1813 July 15
    Mentions the hand bill about British cruelty upon the inhabitants of Virginia, the poor in Maine suffering from lack of bread, and Judge Kelham's request for six mails a week at Wenham
  - William Cutts to Richard Cutts 1847 April 20
    His cousin discusses Cutts Family genealogy
  - Tristram Dalton (1738-1817) to Richard Cutts 1813-1815, 3 ALS
    Asks for his help in securing an appointment and a mortgage on his daughter's land at [Saco?] Falls
  - Judah Dana (1772-1845) to Richard Cutts 1810 December 8
    Requests the establishment of a post road from Fryeburg to Waterford, Maine
  - Samuel Dana (1767-1835) to Richard Cutts 1815 January 28
    Discusses the possible appointment as a commissioner to adjust the Yazoo claims
  - Matthew Livingston Davis (1773-1850) to Richard Cutts 1813 January 18
    Approves of Madison's appointment of General John Armstrong (1758-1843) of New York as Secretary of War; discusses New York politics, particularly De Witt Clinton, mayor of New York City, and the unpopularity of G[ideon?] Granger
  - Henry Dearborn (1751-1829) to Richard Cutts 1803 April 19
    Writes that the King of Spain had sent notice that the United States was to keep its right of deposit at New Orleans on the same footing as it was prior to his orders last autumn, until another agreement could be reached between the two governments
  - Henry Alexander Scammell Dearborn (1783-1851) to Richard Cutts 1814 May 20
    Has paid the duties and freight for the articles on the brig Rambler destined for Mr. and Mrs. Madison; ashamed for the lack of support in Boston for the government and the war against Great Britain; believes that Russia, France, Holland, Spain, and the Italian states have the same interests as the United States in reducing the power and control of Great Britain over the ocean; also predicts another revolution in France.
  - Joseph Delaplaine (1777-1824) to Mrs. Anna Cutts 1819 January 22
    Asks for her to sit for her portrait
  - George William Erving (1771-1850) to Anna Cutts n.y. December 19
    Promises that the parcels intended for James Madison will be taken by Hazlewood Farish to Montpelier or the Orange Courthouse
  - William Eustic (1753-1825) to Richard Cutts and George Ingels 1804-1815, 16 ALS
    Two letters as Secretary of War to Ingels, acknowledging receipts for Indian goods (1811 Dec 24); letters to Cutts include: advice on recruiting for the military force for the War of 1812 (1813 Jan 25); asks about arrangements for his passage to Europe, with a note on the verso page from Benjamin W. Crowninshield (1814 Mar 18); discusses scheme to take Montreal in the winter over the ice (1814 Jun 22); inquires about the records of the War Office and other matters following the burning of Washington by the British (1814 Sep 16); his approval of James Monroe as Secretary of War and of James Madison's speech following the attack on Washington (1814 Oct 5); asks if the account of expenditures spent on the Boston harbor and fortifications for several years could answer the critics of the government who believed Boston had been neglected (1814 Oct 19); discusses the militia bill of [William Branch] Giles (1814 Nov 25); refers to the Battle of New Orleans, "Should they stand & beat the enemy, he & they [his troops] will deserve immortality" (1815 Jan 28 & Feb 13); and describes his arrival in Holland to take up his post as minister to Holland (1815 Nov 26)
  - J. Fairfield to Richard Cutts 1803 February 7
    Writes "since the President's message they [the Federalist Party] have nothing to attend to but separation business"
  - "A Federalist" to James Madison 1813 April 2
    Warns that the British have agents in Washington ready to kill Madison by dagger of poison
  - Timothy Fuller (1778-1835) to Richard Cutts 1821 September 3
    Writes concerning a financial matter
  - Albert Gallatin (1761-1849) to Richard Cutts 1809 February 9
    Asks for his recommendations for the posts of collectors of Saco and Kennebunk
  - Hannah Gallatin to Anna Cutts 1809 September 5
    Sends flannel to Mrs. Cutts and reflects with pleasure on her visit to Montpelier
  - Gideon Gardner (1759-1832) to Richard Cutts 1814 March 5
    Asks that the President permit their vessels to go as far as the Sakonnet River and still be in compliance with the Embargo, and mentions the amount of whale oil carried by several vessels, including one with 1,600 barrels of oil valued at $75,000
  - Christopher Gore to Richard Cutts 1814 March 15
    Forwards letters (not attached) from his district for Cutts to bring before the President as he thought best
  - Robert Goodloe Harper (1765-1825) to [Richard Cutts?] 1815 February 6
    Discusses several legal matters
  - John Holmes (1773-1843) to Richard Cutts 1812-1814, 3 ALS
    Discusses the best way to raise troops (1812-1813) and the effect of the burning of Washington by the British (1814 Sep 19)
  - John G. Jackson to Richard Cutts 1811-1814, 7 ALS
    Writes of financial matters, appointments, and personal news; discusses his salt producing business at Clarksburg, Ohio (1814 Jul 25; Aug 19)
  - Richard Mentor Johnson (1780-1850) to Richard Cutts 1835 October 23
    Advises Cutts on a college for his son
  - [William ?] Jones (1763-1831) to Richard Cutts 1817 January 23
    Offers his services to the branch of the Bank of the United States at Washington
  - Daniel Kelham to Richard Cutts 1814 August 1
    Discusses foreign affairs with Europe, the new reign of Louis XVIII of France, and the opposition of New England to the War of 1812 against Great Britain
  - Cyrus King (1772-1817) to Richard Cutts 1802 Feburary 27
    Discusses the heavy snows, the building of a meeting-house, and plans for a new bank at Portland
  - William King (1768-1852) to Richard Cutts 1804-1810, 3 ALS
    Discusses political appointments, local politics, and the Bank of the United States
  - Isaac Lane, John Holmes, & Daniel Lane to Richard Cutts 1813 January 6 & 23
    Discuss their plans to raise a regiment in York County, Maine
  - John Langdon (1741-1819) to Richard Cutts 1802-1804, 2 ALS
    Expresses his pleasure with the papers and speeches Cutts has sent him and the activities of Congress; reports the election of Nicholas Gilman as Senator (1804)
  - Abraham Lansing to Richard Cutts 1813 April 12
    Explains he was unaware of his appointment until he received the letter from Cutts
  - A.R. Lawrence to Jacob Barker 1813 July 20
    Writing probably as a member of the New York state legislature, he complains that President Madison has not rewarded his friends in New York with patronage and support but his enemies
  - J.D. [Learned ?] to Richard Cutts 1814 January 25
    Complains about the performance of the revenue officers of Maine in curbing smugglers since the beginning of the war; every port is full of British goods; the collector at Castine in contrast has performed his duty well; believes that the British are actively purchasing provisions for their army at the port of Belfast
  - Silas Lee (1760-1814) to Richard Cutts 1802 February 7
    Writes concerning the inconvenience of the dates of the district and state courts
  - William Little to Richard Cutts 1813 July 24
    Seeks the office of collector of the excise taxes at Boston
  - Tobias Lord (1778-1854) to Richard Cutts 1812 December 1
    Offers to build and rig a twenty gun ship for the government by June
  - Isaac Lyman to Richard Cutts 1805 January 10
    Requests assistance in settling the account of the United States with the estate of the late collector, Joseph Tucker
  - Dolley Madison to Richard Cutts 1836 July 5
    Writes shortly after the death of James Madison, thanking him for his sympathy, asks him to visit Mr. Morris of the Highlands and tell him that she valued his friendship and advice, and says of her husband, "I would write but have not power over my confused and oppressed mind to speak fully [the rest?] of the enduring goodness of my beloved husband! - he left me many pledges of his confidence and love especially all his valued writings, from the proceeds of the first part (the Debates in the Convention of 1787) I have to pay donations to several public Institutions"
  - J. Mason to Richard Cutts n.d.
    Discusses the transport of prisoners from Salem to Halifax
  - John Young Mason (1799-1859) to unknown 1831 January [7]
    Discusses the difficulties involved with Virginia tracing her title to disputed Western lands
  - Prentiss Mellen (1764-1840) to Richard Cutts 1802 December 14
    Asks assistance in securing a pension for the widow of John Lee, discharged from the army in 1783; also lists the names of his children
  - Hugh Mercer to James Madison 1827 July 27
    Sends letter of introduction for Joseph W. [Harnum?]
  - William Moody to Richard Cutts 1813-1814, 6 ALS
    Mentions shortages in corn, flour, coffee, and other staples (1813 May 8); the election of Elbridge Gerry as Vice-President, the activities of the Federalists in Massachusetts, and no news of the U.S. frigate Chesapeake (1813 Jun 11); refers to the resolves by [Harrison Gray] Otis supporting Vermont in the bid to recall state militias from the service of the United States and smuggling in New England (1814 Jan 17); and concern over the burning of Washington (1814 Oct 6)
  - James Moorfield to Nancy Moorfield 1830 April 8
    Writes his wife from Havana with personal news and describes in detail the "young queen's" wedding, presumably at Havana
  - James Morrison to Richard Cutts 1815 February 17
    With an attached letter from James Taylor, January 23, 1815, both concerned with helping their friend, Captain Payne, find new employment
  - Charlotte Morton to Anna Cutts 1805 August
    Writing from Montpelier, she congratulates Anna on the birth of her son, and extols the delights of staying at Montpelier, mentioning the house, surroundings, inhabitants, and its extensive library
  - Perez Morton to Richard Cutts 1812 November 11
    Writes of the opposition to the administration in the eastern district of Massachusetts, and of his hopefulness that the effectiveness of President Madison's speech will unite the opposition
  - Sarah Wentworth Apthorpe Morton (1759-1846), wife of Perez Morton, to Mr. & Mrs. Cutts 1805 January 28
    Sends her regards and hopes that her husband will soon be able to return home
  - Hugh Nelson (1768-1836) to Richard Cutts 1815 February 2
    Sends a recommendation for the appointment of Librarian to Congress
  - Francis Noble to Richard Cutts 1814 June 2
    Asks for his help getting permission from the Secretary of State to equip a ship from the port of Boston to carry passengers and mail to England
  - Seth W. Nye to Richard Cutts 1813 April 9
    Asks for a position in the Boston Post Office
  - Josiah Paine to Richard Cutts 1814 January 22
    Writes concerning the appointments of his sons to the navy
  - Daniel Parker to Richard Cutts 1822 August 31
    Has published his opinions about the election in The Boston Patriot
  - John C. Payne to Richard Cutts 1817 November 1
    Thanks Cutts for the newspapers and asks him to send him the publications of some agricultural societies so he can improve the productivity of his fields and garden
  - Major Porter to Captain Truman 1810 August 28, letter heavily damaged
    Requests forms to comply with the request of Mr. Eustis
  - William Pitt Preble (1783-1857) to Richard Cutts 1812-1817, 6 ALS
    Says that the recent elections has made him ashamed of New England, "that patriotism which animated our fathers in the revolution has fled to the backwoods of Kentucky and Ohio," disagrees with the contention that the election of DeWitt Clinton would bring peace, and promises "Fear not Massachusetts - and her satellites - she is almost ashamed to see you carry on the war without her. Forty thousand of her sons have not yet bowed the knee to Baal" (1812 Nov 23); while news of the disaster concerning the forces of James Winchester on the frontier was a terrible blow, he is encouraged by news of the destruction of the British frigate Java (1813 Feb 18); describes a large Republican convention at Alfred, Maine, and welcomes news of the victory of the U.S. Hornet over the British ship The Peacock (1813 Mar 25); mentions the American victories at York (present-day Toronto) and Fort Meigs, and admits to being open to an appointment if his abilities are needed (1813 Jun 2 & 15); and discusses the estate of Foxwell Cutts (1817 Apr 8)
  - Joseph [Prime ?] to Richard Cutts 1813 February 21
    Requests his help in securing an appointment for Franklin Greene as an officer in the army
  - Jesse Putnam to Richard Cutts 1813 July 20
    Asks for his help in applying for the office of collector at Boston
  - Josiah Quincy (1772-1864) to Benjamin Eaton 1806 February 12
    Writes concerning Eaton's petition to Benjamin Crowninshield
  - A. Randolph to her sister, Harriet Hackley 1831 April 17
    Asks for her help in completing shirts for her son George before he sails
  - Richard Poland Randolph to Dolley Madison 1845 September 13
    Writes from the Washington City Prison, relating the details of his incarceration and begging for her help
  - Silvestre [Rebello ?] to Anna Cutts 1827 June 13
    Presents Mrs. Cutts with another pack of snuff to be shared with her sister
  - David Sewall (1735-1825) to Richard Cutts 1803 December 17
    Discusses a controversy about the appointment of General Commissioner of Bankruptcy for the District of Maine
  - Samuel Shaw (1768-1827) to Richard Cutts 1812-1814, 3 ALS
    Believes that Madison is popular in Vermont (1812 Jan 21); the Senate has confirmed the army appointment of Henry Dearborn (1812 Jan 28); and says that the "success of [Andrew] Jackson and the peace" has confounded the opposition (1815 Feb 27)
  - M[argaret] B. Smith to Richard Cutts n.d.
    Sends a book as a gift and thanks him for his true and sincere friendship
  - Samuel L. Southard (1787-1842) to Midshipman Walter C. Coles 1828 August 1
    Sends orders for his naval service
  - Robert Southgate to Richard Cutts 1803 January 30
    Sends his condolence over the death of Cutts' mother
  - William Stackpole (1779-1822) to Richard Cutts 1812 November 19
    Discusses his insurance policy on The Yorrick
  - David Starwood to Richard Cutts 1814 July 19
    Defends Colonel L.D. Learned against charges of improper conduct while contracting for cartridge boxes
  - Sarah Coles Stevenson, wife of Andrew Stevenson, U.S. minister to Great Britain, to Dolley Madison 1839 January 26
    Describes her travels in Great Britain, particularly Scotland, and furnishes details about the young Queen Victoria; mentions the publication of Mr. Madison's works and that Mrs. Coolidge goes to China in March
  - Seth Storer to Richard Cutts 1810 December 5
    Has safely arrived from London at Norfolk, and asks his opinions about the future of trade with either France or England
  - James Sullivan (1744-1808) to Richard Cutts 1804 December 8 & 30
    Asks that the Cutts look out for his son, George, now visiting Washington, congratulates Cutts on the election, and believes Albert Gallatin a man of much ability
  - Peleg Tallman (1764-1840) to Richard Cutts 1813 March 20
    Sends letter of introduction for Dr. John Martin
  - William Temple to [Anna ?] Payne 1797 February 4
    Mentions the interruption of the commerce of the United States by the French and assures her that he has all of her letters and will get them to her as soon as he can find a proper conveyance
  - George Thatcher to Richard Cutts 1802 January 20
    Asks him to pay his subscription to The Universal Gazette and send him copies of reports from Congress
  - David Thomas (1762-1831) to Richard Cutts 1812 January 4
    Forwards a request for an appointment to army by David Thomas
  - Thomas Todd (1765-1826) to Richard Cutts 1817-1822, 5 ALS